Most food crops are contaminated
with fungal mycotoxins.
Watch the video to find out how
much of a problem this may be.
"Ochratoxin and Breakfast Cereals,
Herbs, Spices, and Wine"
In France, exposure to dietary
contaminants was compared between
vegetarians and meat-eaters, and
the results showed that exposures
to persistent organic pollutants
like PCBs and dioxins
was dramatically lower among
those eating more plant-based
due to the non-consumption
of foods of animal origins—
though they did have
higher estimated exposure
to some mycotoxins, fungal
toxins present in moldy food.
Now, there are lots types of mold
on the planet, and the vast majority
are harmless, but over the last
several years certain mold toxins,
such as aflatoxin and ochratoxin,
have been popping up
in breakfast cereals.
Hundreds of samples were
taken off store shelves,
and about half were contaminated
with ochratoxin, for example;
but those were store
shelves in Pakistan.
And Pakistan has a sub-tropical climate
with monsoons and ﬂash ﬂoods,
leading to fungal propagation.
But then similar results
have popped up in Europe,
Serbia, Spain, Portugal.
Then mycotoxins were discovered
in breakfast cereals in Canada.
What about breakfast cereals
in the United States?
144 samples were collected,
and similar to other countries
about half were found
to contain ochratoxin,
but only about 7% exceeded
the maximum limit
established by the
European Commission.
What is the signiﬁcance
of the finding of ochratoxin
in breakfast cereals
from the United States?
This was the largest study to date,
including nearly 500 samples
of cereal off store
shelves across the U.S.
Overall detection rates were
about 40%, though only 16 violated
the European standards, all
the cereals with ochratoxin were
oat-based, making about
1 in 13 of the oat-based
breakfast cereal samples
tested being contaminated.
Ochratoxin has become increasingly
regulated by many countries
to minimize chronic exposure.
Here are the current regulations
for mycotoxins in cereal-based
baby foods worldwide, for example.
Some countries are very strict,
like in the European Union,
other countries less so,
and one country in particular
has no standards at all.
Ochratoxin is not currently
regulated at all in the United States.
What if you stick to organic products?
One might expect them to
actually be worse, owing to the fact
that fungicides are not
allowed in organic production.
However, mycotoxin concentrations
are usually similar or even
reduced in organic compared
with conventional products.
For example, in one of the
breakfast cereal studies,
researchers found similar
contamination,
and the same was
found for infant foods.
It cannot be concluded
that one is better
than the other from a
mycotoxin perspective.
Despite no use of fungicides,
organic systems appear generally
able to maintain mycotoxin
contamination at low levels.
But how much is that saying
given how widespread it is?
How concerned should we be
about the public health effects
from long-term exposure
of this potent mycotoxin?
If you look at blood samples taken
from populations going back decades,
sometimes 100% of people turn
up positive for ochratoxin
circulating in their bloodstream.
In some sense they are
unavoidable contaminants of food,
since the detection of
mycotoxins is not always easy
and they can remain hidden.
And once foods have
become contaminated,
mycotoxins aren’t
destroyed by cooking.
So, are there some foods we
should simply try to avoid
due to higher risk of contamination?
That’s exactly the question
I’m going to address next.
Oats can be thought of as uniquely
nutritious, and one route
they improve human health is
by providing prebiotics
that increase the growth of
beneficial gut microbiota.
Of course, there are oats
and then there are oats,
ranging from steel-cut oats, to
even better, intact oat groats
(their form before being cut),
all the way down
to highly processed cereals
such as Honey Nut Cheerios.
Rolling crushes the grain
which may disrupt cell walls
and damage starch granules making
them more available for digestion,
which is bad, since we want
the starch to make it all
the way down to our colon to
feed our good gut bacteria.
Grinding into oat flour to make
breakfast cereals is even worse.
If you compare the blood sugar
and insulin responses, you can see
significantly lower spikes with
the more intact steel-cut oats.
Okay, but what about ochratoxin?
The leading source
of dietary exposure of
this mold contaminant, but
they aren’t the only source.
There’s a worldwide contamination
of food crops with mycotoxins,
with some experts
throwing around estimates
as high as 25% of the world’s crops.
That statistic is attributed to
the Food and Agriculture Organization
of the United Nations, but it
turns out that statistic is bogus.
It’s not 25%. Instead, it
may be more like 60 to 80%.
The high occurrence is
likely explained by a combination
of the improved sensitivity
of testing methods
as well as the impact
of climate change.
Spices have been found to have
some of the highest concentrations
of mycotoxins, but because they
are ingested in such small quantities,
they’re not considered
to be a signiﬁcant source.
We can certainly do our
part to minimize risk, though.
It is also the consumers’
responsibility to keep spices dry
after opening sealed
containers or packages.
What about dried herbs?
Mycotoxins in plant-based dietary
supplements: the highest mycotoxin
concentrations were found in
milk thistle-based supplements.
It turns out wet and
humid weather is needed
during milk thistle harvest,
which evidently is why
they end up being so moldy.
Considering the fact that milk
thistle preparations are mainly used
by people who suﬀer from
a liver disease, such high intake
of compounds toxic to the
liver may present some concern.
Wine sourced from the United
States also appears to have
particularly high levels.
In fact, the single highest level
found to date around the world
is in American wine, but there’s
contamination in wine in general.
In fact, some suggest that’s
why we see such consistent levels
in people’s blood—perhaps because lots
of people are regular wine drinkers.
Ochratoxin is said to be a kidney
toxin with immunosuppressive,
birth defect-causing, and
carcinogenic properties.
So, what about ochratoxin decontamination—
removing the toxin—in wine?
Now ideally, we’d try to prevent
the contamination in the first place,
but since this isn’t always
practical there is increased focus
on finding effective methods
of detoxification of mycotoxins
already present in foods.
And that’s where yeast
comes in as a promising solution,
because the mycotoxins bind
to the yeast cell wall.
The thought is that you could strain
out the yeast, but another approach
would be to eat something
like nutritional yeast
to prevent the absorption.
It works in chickens.
Give yeast along with aflatoxin
(another mycotoxin),
and you diminish the severity
of the resulting disease.
But using something like nutritional
yeast as a binder depends on the
stability of the yeast-mycotoxin
bond throughout the digestive tract.
We know yeasts can remove ochratoxin
in foods, but we didn’t have a clue
if it would work in the gut until 2016.
Yeast was found to bind up to 44%
of the ochratoxin, but in actuality
it was probably closer
to only about a third
since some of the
bindings weren’t stable.
So, if you’re trying to stay
under the maximum daily intake
and you drink a single glass
of wine, even if your bar snack
is popcorn seasoned
with nutritional yeast,
you’d still probably exceed
the tolerable intake.
But what does that mean? How bad
is this stuff? We’ll find out next.